Kill the Armed Librarians!
武装司書を殺せ
Sorry. But you're two seconds late!
残念　２秒遅い
Damn. Closing time, huh?
チェ　店じまいか
Gentlemen, the last drink is on me.
諸君　俺のおごりだ
本影音版权属其出版、发行方，字幕制作仅供学术交流之用 请于下载后24小时内删除，并不得有公开传播或作商业盈利之行为 若有违法等相关行为，诸神字幕组恕不承担任何法律或连带责任。
Enjoy every last drop!
最後の一杯　遠慮なくやってくれ
翻译 koki  放 晴  La Fatalité
So he's this ship's commanding officer?
そいつがこの船の指揮官だな
So it would seem...
そうみたいだけど
压制 暗之亚瑟王  校对 凉YAN Lucifer 时间 Lucifer
Answer me. Why must the Armed Librarians die?
教えてくれ　なぜ俺達武装司書が死ななきゃならん？
Because Noloty died!
ノロティが死んだからだ
え　また？
Another one?
Noloty died, and now so will you!
ノロティは死んだ　お前たちも死ね
All Armed Librarians should rot in hell!
武装司書はみんな死ね
Then let me change the question.
では質問を変える　お前はノロティ＝マルチェと知り合いなのか
Did you and Noloty Malche know one another?
Who is Noloty?
ノロティとは誰だ　いつどこで会った
Where and when did you meet?
答えてみろ　さ　早く
Answer me.
Now!
I-I...
わ、わたしは…
Wh-What's going on?
ど、どうなってんの
They all give the same answer!
どいつもこいつも同じ返事ばっか
Yes... So what connection
do they have to Noloty?
あ　ノロティと何の関係が？
诸
神字幕组
剥がれ落ちた夢 澱む幻
The dream that's fallen away
and the stagnant illusion
もう この世界を見放した者さえ
The words embrace even the ones
who have abandoned this world
包み込む言葉
刹那に消えゆく
Disappearing instantly
共に囚われの明日を取り戻そう
Let's take back the imprisoned
tomorrow together
何もかも失くしても
Even if we lose everything
最期の審議の日まで　ずっと
Until the judgment day
Keep on blooming proudly like flowers
花のように強く咲き誇れ
絶望のオト　拾い集めて
Pick up the sounds of despair
永久に奏でる　ストレインに変える
Play it forever and change it into strain
I'll stick around, clinging onto the subtle light
僅かなヒカリ　すがりついても
留まるから
届けたい　残らず
I want to convey it until there's nothing left
Episode 21
Enmity, the Color Blue, and the Rope Princess
第21话 憎恨
与
深蓝
和
草绳公主
It's been one day since war broke out.
開戦より一昼夜
連合軍とバントーラ図書館は今だ激しい攻防戦を繰り広げております
Bantorra Library and the Allied Forces advance
ever deeper into brutal tactical combat.
残念　行っちゃえ　シュラムッフェン
Sucks to be you!
Go get 'em, Shlamuffen!
Looks like he bought us some more time.
どうやら　命拾いしたな
And giving Shlamuffen to Rithly...
けど　リズリーさんにシュラムッフェンって
The perfect weapon for such
an evil-minded person.
腹黒いあの人にはぴったりの武器ね
Are you okay?!
大丈夫か
Damn you...
くそ　畜生
Damn it! How long
will this go on?
いつまで続くんだよ
The enemy is everywhere.
四方八方敵ばかり
Everyone pulled together somehow
みんなの頑張りで
and managed to stop the fleet about
fifty kilometers from shore.
なんとか島より約五十キロの海域に艦隊を足止めしていますが
At this rate, it's only a matter of
time before they make land.
このままじゃ　いずれ上陸されるも時間の問題ね
Hamyuts, we must embark, too.
ハミュッツさん　私たちも出るわよ
This is no time to hold back
our offensive powers.
もう戦力を温存している場合じゃないわ
Okay.
OK
We'll start our strike with the western
Guinbecs's fleet and advance from there.
じゃあ　まずは西のグインベクス艦隊から叩き捲る
Hold on a second. Then who will...
待って下さい　では誰が…
Milepoc, I am designating you
Supreme Commander until my return.
ミレポ　私が戻るまで　あんたに全指揮権を委任するわ
What?
え？
You can handle it.
適任ね
I'll take care of everything,
so just act as you see fit.
責任はすべてあたしが取るから　思うようにやりなさい
I will leave this with you, as well.
こいつも預けとくからね
これは…
But that's...
Just to be safe. Good luck.
念のためよ　宜しく
What? The enemy soldiers
all say Noloty's name?
え　敵兵たちがみんなノロティさんの名を
Any idea what that means, old lady?
何か心当たりある　お婆ちゃん
She would never betray us!
あの子が裏切るなんてありえません
正義感は人一倍の子だったし
Her sense of righteousness was
stronger than anyone's.
It really was...
そうようね
Though she drove me crazy at times...
本当に手を焼かされたけど
ここ１０年で　私の言う事を聞かなかったのはあの子だけ
In my ten years here, she was the only
one who disobeyed my orders.
It's impossible for you.
あなたには無理よ
Even if you manage to become an
Armed Librarian, you will die.
万が一武装司書になれたとしても必ず死ぬわ
死にません　必ず強くなります
I will not die!
I will become strong!
そう　なら私も決断が必要ね
I see. In that case, I must
determine something myself.
私はあなたが可愛い
I truly care about you.
I cannot bear to see you killed at the
hands of someone uninteresting!
つまらない相手に　殺されるのも見たくない
そんなもの？
Seriously? That's all you've got?
あなたの「本気」は？
Go ahead and die.
死になさい
You still don't have it in you.
これでも駄目なのね
Even at the very edge of death,
生きるか死ぬかの瀬戸際でもまだ
your fists lacked the resolve to kill me.
あなたの拳には　私を殺そうとする気迫がなかった
It's not a matter of stubbornness, either.
強情とかそういう問題じゃない
ねえ　あなたみたいな子をどうすればいいの？
Tell me, what do I do with a girl like you?
ねえ　ノロティ
Tell me, Noloty.
Yes, to be frank, she had not a
speck of aptitude within her.
そう　はっきり言ってノロティさんには
才能の欠片もなかった
I tried so many times to make her quit.
何度もやめさせようとしたわ
But she was a truly mysterious girl.
けど　本当に不思議な子
I was sure it would be impossible for her,
絶対に無理だと思ったはずのことが
but then one day, it suddenly seemed possible.
いつのまにか無理じゃなくなっている
I've been an Armed Librarian
longer than anyone,
私は武装司書で一番長いけど
and yet I had never met someone like her.
あんな子は初めて
So it would be fair to say, if she had lived,
じゃあ　ひょっとして
生きていればあたしやあなたを超える日が来たかもね
she might have surpassed us someday?
Yes.
えー　まさかと言いたいところだけど
The very thought frightens me,
but the sky might have been the limit for her.
あの子に限っては　あり得たかも
Hey. I need to ask you this.
ねえ　一つ聞きたいんだけどさ
Am I smiling right now?
あたし　今笑ってる？
What?
え？　いいえ
Not at all.
What's going on with me, then?
I'm such a weirdo.
なんでかしらね
変なのよ　あたし
I know I'd normally find this fun.
楽しくないわけじゃないし　むしろ一番楽しいはずなのに
Heck, it should be the most
fun thing in the world.
Hamyuts, may I ask you one question, then?
ハミュッツさん
では私にも一つだけ聞かせてちょうだい
Hmm?
ずっと不思議だった
This has always confused me.
Why do you always rush toward death?
一体なぜあなたはそんなに死に急いでるの
Why did you become an Armed Librarian?
なぜ武装司書に
What was your goal?
目的は
By whom and where were you raised? And...
どこの誰があなたを育って
そして…
That's more than one question.
質問は一つだけじゃなかったっけ
Entering the battle zone.
まもなく戦闘空域です
Please ready yourselves for battle.
お二人とも　ご準備を
Alrighty then.
そうね
Maybe I'll answer your questions,
まあ　お互い生き残る事ができたら
if we both survive.
教えてあげちゃうかも
They keep coming!
きりがねえ　帰った早々
Sent to battle just as we got home...
The Acting Director is such a slave-driver!
人使いが荒いよな　代行も
Seriously.
まったくだ
見ろよ　あの青い空　白い雲
Look at that blue sky and those white clouds.
正しく死ぬには打って付けの日だぜ
It's a perfect day to die.
Don't try to sound all cool.
格好つけてじゃねえよ
Ireia!
イレイアさん
I am disgusted.
嘆かわしい
I didn't raise you boys to quit so easily!
そんなに諦めのいい子達に育てた覚えはありません
Impatient little boys...
せっかちな殿方には
must be punished!
お仕置きが必要ね
Sheesh.
へ　やれやれ
Guess that means it's time for our second wind.
もうひと頑張ると行くか　俺らも
Yeah!
おー
Ah... What a mess.
おーお　派手なこと
Noloty's dead!
ノロティが死んだ
Kill the Armed Librarians!
武装司書に死を
This is so bizarre.
本当に変
I've been waiting for this day to come,
and yet I feel nothing.
この日を待ち望んでたはずなのに　全然…
Still...
けど…
I guess I'll let you humor me.
我慢してあげる　ちゃちゃっと気合入れてぶっ殺してね
Try and kill me with everything you've got.
このあたしを
Noloty came from the mountains
in the southern hinterlands.
ノロティさんはね　南方辺境の山間の出身なの
She said it was a tiny village, with no
occupations besides tilling the land.
田を耕す以外　何の産業もない小さな村だと言ってたわ
Brace yourself. I'm going to
tell you something wild.
驚きなさい　すごいことを教えてあげる
あの子　村ではお姫様だったのよ
She was a princess in her village!
Huh?
あ？
小さな村なんですけどね
It really was a tiny village, though.
What was your last wish,
which never came true?
叶わなかった　お前の最後の願いとは…
What're you doing...
なんだよ
You're so light.
あ　軽い
Put me down! Don't treat me like a kid!
下ろせ　子ども扱いするな
Noloty, are you out wasting time somewhere?
ノロティ　あなたどこで遊んでいるのよ
Ah, Milepoc!
あ　ミレポックさん
According to the report, you solved that
bio-terror plot already, didn't you?
報告だと　細菌テロ事件はとっくに解決したのよね
A- Ah, yes.
あ、はい　あの…えと…　ちょっと気になることがあって
Uh, um... Something caught my eye, so...
今一人で調べる最中なんですけど
I'm looking into it right now, alone.
All right. But call for backup
if you get into any danger.
いいわ　但し危なくなったらすぐに救援を呼んで　いいわな
Understood?
R-Roger!
了解
You were talking about killing me, weren't you?
俺を殺すこと　相談してたんだろう
Huh? Not at all.
え　そんなことないよ
嘘だ　武装司書はいつもそうだ
You lie! That's all you Armed
Librarians think about.
Yours looks better than mine.
そっちのほうがいい
ならこっとも食べなよ
Then eat mine, too.
It's cold, and the air is dry.
寒いし　空気は乾燥してるから
If you don't get enough fluids,
your body will weaken.
たくさん飲まないと　体壊すよ
Kachua might kill me, too.
カチュアに殺されるかもな　俺も
He'll be angry that I'm traveling with you.
お前なんかを連れてたら怒る
Then I'll defeat Kachua for you.
なら　あたしがカチュアを倒してあげる
But you'll be killed by one of
your fellow Armed Librarians
お前は他の武装司書に殺されるだろう
for being my minion.
俺の手下になったんだから
Huh?
えー　大丈夫だと思うけど
I-I think I'll be okay.
Though I really don't wanna get demoted...
でも降格はいやだな　まだ借金も返してないのに
I still have loans to pay off.
I like this!
いい気味だ
死んでしまえ　武装司書
Rot in hell, Armed Librarian.
馬鹿が馬鹿やって死ぬなら　最高だ
Nothing better than watching
an idiot die like an idiot.
All right!
よーし　あともうちょっと
We're almost there.
Um, I'd rather you didn't do that.
あのう　そういうことはしないでほしいな
What's your deal?!
なんなんだよ　お前は
Why don't you get angry?
Are you missing a few screws up here?
何で怒らないんだ　頭おかしいのか
なんでお前みたいなのが武装司書をやってる
Why is someone like you an Armed Librarian?
は？
Huh?
Does someone like you actually do those things?
それとも　お前みたいなのでもあんなことするのか？
Killing people for no reason and
buying lives with money...
理由もなく人を殺して　命を金で買うのか？
あんなことって？
Those things?
Arkit, you're out for revenge, right?
アーキット　復讐…なんだね
Yes. For no reason at all, the Armed Librarians
killed those dearest to me.
そうだ
武装司書は俺の大事な人たちを何の理由もなく殺した
Who and when?
誰がいつ？
Who did the killing?
誰が殺したの？
誰を殺したの？
Who did they kill?
I won't understand if you don't explain!
言ってくれなきゃ分からないよ
分かってほしいと誰が言った
When did I say I wanted you to understand?
It's true that fighting is in an
Armed Librarian's job description.
武装司書は確かに戦うのは仕事だよ
人を殺すことだってある
And sometimes that involves killing.
But that is only when there is no other option!
でも　それは殺さなきゃならない時だけだよ
You're lying!
嘘だ
How... How can even you say such things?
どうして　どうしてお前までそんなこと言うんだ？
I thought you'd understand!
お前なら分かると思ったのに
Who's there?
誰？
I am the Governor of Paradise, the leader
of the Church of Drowning in God's Grace.
神溺教団の総帥「楽園管理者」
My name is Kachua Beenhas.
名を　カチュア＝ビーインハスと言う
Hold on a moment, Noloty Malche.
待ちなさい　ノロティ＝マルチェ
I have come to talk with you.
私は話し合いに来たのだ
I cannot trust you!
信用できない
なるほど　ならばこうしよう
I see. In that case, let me do this.
私の能力は他人の認識を操る力
My power allows me to manipulate
others' perceptions.
これなら　無防備なただの老人にすぎない
With this, I will appear to be merely
a defenseless, old man.
What do you want to tell me?
何の話をしに
I am revealing myself to you,
after consistently running away.
逃げ回っていた私が姿を現した
What else could it be about?
する話など決まっている
The Church wishes to surrender
to the Armed Librarians.
神溺教団は武装司書に降伏する　それを伝えに来た
I came to tell you that.
Huh?
なぜ？
Why?
ハハ　今度はなぜときたか
You wish to know why, do you?
You people are the ones who have driven
us to the brink of annihilation.
ほかならぬ　君たちの手で
我々はすでに壊滅寸前まで追い込まれているというのに
If you know that, then why not surrender earlier?
そこまで分かってるなら
どうしてもっと早く降伏しなかったの
A war isn't something easily called off.
戦いというものはそうおいそれとやめられるものではない
The people beneath me will not
understand why we're surrendering.
降伏しようと言ったところで　部下たちが納得せんよ
However, a decision has finally been reached.
だが　ようやく決心がついた
Will you not trust me, Noloty?
信じてもらえるかな　ノロティ
Very well. I'll accept your surrender.
分かった　降伏を受け入れる
Return to Bantorra Library with me
and reveal all the Church's secrets.
バントーラ図書館に同行して
神溺教団の秘密を全てはかしなさい
Absolutely. However, I do
have a request for you.
かまわん
ただし君に頼みがある
Regarding us bringing the war to an end...
我らの戦いの締め括りさ
I would like you to rectify
a mistake that we made.
私の過ちの後始末をしてもらいたい
What are you talking about?
なんのこと？
I want you to kill Arkit Chloma.
アーキット＝クロマを殺してくれ
Why is this happening to us?
どうしてこんなことになったの
It'll be all right.
The Armed Librarians will protect us.
大丈夫よ　きっと武装司書の皆が守ってくれる
Have no fear, Yukizona!
お兄様　どうぞご心配なく
I'll do it.
やっている
ユーリもまだまだ戦います　安心してお任せあれ
I will continue to fight.
You can count on me!
I said I would do it.
だからやっている
Get down, Yuri!
下がれ　ユーリ
はい
Okay!
大丈夫ですか
Are you okay?
Their numbers are not easily overcome.
数はこれほど厄介なものとはな
Minth! Minth!
ミンスさん　ミンスさん
Tsamuro, Hony, take the
northwest Ronar fleet.
ザムル　ホニーは北線のローナ艦隊を
Do not let them advance beyond
thirty kilometers east.
東側30キロ　防衛線維持
Kyzal, Balan, Tena, Clad,
I want you four to...
キャサリロ　バラ　テナ　クラノム四名は…
Hello, Acting Director here.
なー　こちら代行
押してとくけど　ちょいと死んでとくなってきたよな
I hate to butt in, but I'm a little worried.
Is it Ireia?
イレイアさんですか
And this makes twenty ships!
これで20隻目
I really wish we could stay young forever.
年は取りたくないものね
Care to let me take over, old lady?
お婆ちゃん　下がろ
I can't! If I step out now, Bantorra will...
駄目よ　今引いたらバントーラが…
Just incredible, old lady.
すごいわね　お婆ちゃん
I have the utmost respect for you.
尊敬するわ
I can't leave the battle now...
戻るわけには…
Ireia, don't do too much.
イレイアさん　無理は考えないでください
Your role now is to rest.
今は休みのが戦います
All right...
分かったわ
We're completely outnumbered.
俺たちは数で劣っている
Maybe we shouldn't have split up our forces.
戦力を分散すべきではなかったかも
Issue the retreat, Milepoc.
退却じゃ　ミレポ
Recall the troops.
みんなを呼び戻せ
Minth! Where have you been all this time?
ミンスさん　今までどこに
I'm sorry. I was being chased by some
Mock Men from the Church.
すまぬ
教団の「擬人」のともに追われて
I was in no position to use telepathy.
「思考共有」どころじゃなかったわ
But I figured out what's going on in this battle.
じゃが　この戦争のからくりが分ったぞ
Huh?
え？
The soul of every soldier attacking the
island is filled with unfathomable hatred.
島を襲っとる兵隊ともの魂は全員　とてつもない憎しみに満ちとる
But that's not all.
それだけじゃない　どの人間も魂の色形が同じなんじゃ
All of their souls are the same color.
Their dominant trait is rage.
相は憤　思考は憎しみ　望みはわしら武装司書の滅亡
Their thoughts are of enmity.
And they wish for the Armed
Librarians' annihilation.
And their souls are blue.
そして魂の色は蒼
Blue?
蒼？
Don't tell me you've forgotten. It just happened!
覚えがあるじゃろう
黒細菌じゃ
Yes! The Cerulean Death!
おー　「蒼淵呪病」よ
The infectious disease that directly
manipulates one's soul.
魂に直接作用する伝染病
教団はあの病原体を利用してみんなに憎しみを身つけとるんじゃ
The Church is using it to manipulate everyone
and instill in them feelings of hatred!
My, what a beautiful sunset.
まあ　なんてきれいな夕焼け
あ　みなさんね
Oh... Fear not, everyone.
安心なさい　私たちは負けませんよ
We will not lose.
戻って　安全な場所にいるのがあなたたちの戦いよ
Head back. It's your role to
remain in a safe place.
Blue...
蒼い
Huh?
Kill the Armed Librarians!
武装司書を殺せ
Kill them! The Armed Librarians!
殺せ　武装司書を
Old lady?
お婆ちゃん
Wh-What the heck just happened?
な、何事じゃ　おい？
Ireia... How could they get you too?
イレイアさん　あなたまで…
Come in, Milepoc.
応答せねば　増援を寄こせ
Send reinforcements! We won't last like this.
このままじゃ持たない
町の連中が正門に殺到しています
The townspeople have rushed the main gate!
Are you sure we should be doing this?!
やっちまっていいんですか　これ
The whole island is blue.
島が　蒼く
全武装司書に通達
This is a message for all Armed Librarians!
Everyone is to leave the front lines.
すべての防衛線を放棄
Leave your battle posts and retreat
to Bantorra Library at once!
出撃中の全武装司書は直ちにバントーラ図書館へ撤退
What did she say?
なんだと
No way!
うそ
I repeat, everyone is to evacuate the front lines.
繰り返す
すべての防衛線を放棄　全武装司書は直ちに撤退
All Armed Librarians are to return!
Is she serious?
まじかよ
Hurry!
急げ
Establishing a mist barrier!
無縛結界を発動します
Leave the front lines and return
to fortify the castle!
防衛戦に捨て籠城戦に移ります
This order carries the same weight
as one from the Acting Director!
これは代行命令と同格の権限を持っています
Obey it at once!
今すぐ従ってください
Kill the Armed Librarians!
武装司書を殺せ
Within Arkit lies the power to instill
his hatred into others' souls.
アーキットの中には
自分の憎しみを他人の魂に移植する力が眠っている
If unleashed, his hatred will spread across
the world like an infectious disease.
発動すれば
彼の憎しみは伝染病の如く全世界に広がっていく
I've thought about it, and this power may
be able to defeat the Armed Librarians.
この力で武装司書を倒せぬかと考えた
However, this is not a power to be used in war.
だがこれは　戦力として用いられるような力ではない
武装司書のみならず　世界中を滅ぼしてしまうだろう
It may lead to the entire world's destruction,
not just the Armed Librarians'.
どうした　ノロティ
What is it, Noloty?
What are you doing? It's the middle of the night.
なにやってんだ　こんな夜中に
Your only option is to kill him,
殺すしかない
to save the Armed Librarians and the world.
武装司書　世界を救うには
Stop! Don't listen to him, Noloty!
止せ　耳を貸すな　ノロティ
It's a trap!
それは罠だ
Was this our only choice?
これしかなかったの
You made the right call.
君の判断は正しい
いよいよあとがなくなったわね
This'll finally bring an end to this mess.
We've received no word from
the Armed Librarians.
武装司書からの情報は届いておりません
How many forces remain on Bantorra?
バントーラに残された戦力は…
How many Armed Librarians
have been ripped to shreds?
武装司書は何人打ち殺され…
Excuse me.
失礼
I meant died, no...
死んで…
いや
Die, Armed Librarians!
死ね
武装司書は　死ね死ね死ね…
Die! Die! Die! Die! Die!
Yes! Yes, we did it!
やった　やったぞ
武装司書が滅ぶんだぞ
The Armed Librarians will be destroyed!
Oh, are you awake now,
おや　お目覚めかね
Arkit?
アーキット
A feather in the air captures the dream
It's swimming in the darkness,
pretending to be flying
Let's ask the sad blue sky for the answer
Bang on the closing door (Forcefully)
Sneak out and greet for one last time
"Who did you keep on search for?"
I'm lost for words and don't know the answer
Because of the broken love
Now I've lost everything
An angel will no longer come
Dominant Space
The tears shed at the worst possible ending
最悪な結末に流れる涙に
The Sky,
The tears shed at the worst possible ending
will cleanse all the world's sins.
全ての罪は現れる
The Sky, an Ending,
憎しみの消えた世界では
In a world where hatred is no more,
the footprints will soon fade.
やがて　足跡も消えていく
The Sky, an Ending, and a Girl's World
the footprints will soon fade.
天空与终结和她的世界
The Sky, an Ending, and a Girl's World